Guide to the Asher B. Durand Print Collection 1813-1835, undated PR 221
New-York Historical Society
Asher B. Durand print collection
1813-1835, undated
New-York Historical Society
PR 221
0.46 Linear feet (2 boxes + 6 oversize flat files)
The collection holds copies of prints engraved by Durand, or engraved by others after paintings by Durand.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of various donors, including Lucy Durand Woodman, daughter of the artist, and her daughter, Nora Durand Woodman.
Arrangement
Engravings are grouped by size.
Related Materials
Other engravings by Durand may be found throughout the Portrait File (PR 052), as well as in other print collections in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections. Especially notable is his portrait of John Quincy Adams, in PR 052. The Asher B. Durand Negative Collection (PR 165) includes glass negatives showing interior views of Durand's studio. The Library holds many books with illustrations by Durand, including two copies of Bryant's The American Landscape. The New-York Historical Society's Museum holds many of Durand's paintings and decorative arts, as well as a set of engraving tools used by him.
Scope and Contents
The Asher B. Durand Print Collection holds copies of prints engraved by Durand, or engraved by others after paintings by Durand. The collection is divided into two series: Boxed Prints and Oversize Prints. Therein prints are filed by title or by general subject.
Included in the collection are early engravings made by Durand in 1813 while an apprentice in the shop of Peter Maverick. From the years 1824 to 1832, Durand made a living as a bank note engraver under the firms A.B. & C. Durand & Co., A.B. & C. Durand, Wright & Co., and Durand, Perkins & Co. Many of these engravings and vignettes are included here. Book and magazine illustrations in the collection include the title page to the New-York Mirror (used from 1831-1840) and a copy of William Cullen Bryant's The American Landscape, for which Durand engraved views. Portraits of famous Americans engraved by Durand are arranged alphabetically. Four of Durand's major plates are represented: classical subjects "Musidora" and "Ariadne;" a portrait of Andrew Jackson after John Vanderlyn; and a scene of the signing of the "Declaration of Independence" after John Trumball. The collection also includes several prints engraved by other artists after Durand's landscape paintings.
Bank note vignettes.; Certificates.; Engravings (prints); Illustrations.; Paper money.; Ariadne (Greek mythology) -- Art.; Engraving -- Printing -- Specimens.; A. B. & C. Durand & Co.; A. B. & C. Durand, Wright & Co.; Durand, Perkins & Co.
- Series I: Boxed Prints
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains smaller format works that are housed in boxes.
  - The American Landscape, 1830 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bank notes, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bank note vignettes, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book and magazine illustrations, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates and miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engravings after Durand paintings, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    General note
    See also: Folder 14
  - Portraits, sitters A-G, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Portraits of: Commodore Bainbridge; Joel Barlow; General Brown(?); Charles Carroll of Carrollton; Cadwallader D. Colden (2); Samuel H. Cox; David Crockett (3); Stephen Decatur (2); Rev. James B. Finley; William Floyd; Rev. Freeborn Garrettson; William Gaston (2); Edward Gibbon (2).
  - Portraits, sitters H-M, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Portraits are: Mr. Hackett (2); Hamilton (bust) (2); Rev. Elijah Hedding; Philip Hone; David Hosack; John Jay; Thomas Jefferson; Georgius Jones (2); James Kent; Rev. Sylvester Larned; Morgan Lewis; Ma-nuncue; Joseph Mountjoy Manners; John Marshall (2); John M. Mason; Rev. Alexander McLeod; Rev. Philip Milledoler; Rev. James Milnor; Samuel L. Mitchill; James Monroe; Lindley Murray.
  - Portraits, sitters N-Z, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    Portraits are: Aaron Ogden 92); Rev. William Phoebus; W.(?) Renssalaer; Rem Rapelje (photograph of engraving); Robert C. Sands (3); Rev. James Saurin (2); Catharine M. Sedgwick (4); Rev. Joshua Soule(?); J. Summerfield; William Tell; George Washington (3); Rev. John Wesley; Hugh Williamson; Oliver Wolcott
  - Portraits. Various (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9A)
    Portraits are: Rev. Eliphalet Nott (painted by Ames, 1820); Rev. James B. Finley (painted by J. Paradise); Rev. Joshua Soule (Paradise pinx); James Kent LL.D (painted by F.R. Spencer); and from paintings by J. Neagle: Mrs. Barnes as Isabella, Mr. Cowell as Crack, Mr. Duff as Marmion, Mr. E. Forrest as Rolla, and Mr. Macready as Macbeth.
    Immediate source of acquisition:
    The contents of the folder were the gift of Stephen Manheimer, 2021. Added to the collection and finding aid by archivist Larry Weimer in September 2021.
- Series II: Oversize Prints
  Series II contains larger format works that are housed in flat file drawers.
  - "Declaration of Independence" after Trumbull, 1820 (Folder FF-10)
    Two copies of proof plate, two copies of finished print, one copy of key, one prospectus issued by Trumbull.
  - "General Andrew Jackson" after Vanderlyn, 1828 (Folder FF-11)
  - "Ariadne" after Vanderlyn, 1835 (Folder FF-12)
    One copy before letters, one copy of finished print.
  - "Musidora", 1825 (Folder FF-13)
    Four copies.
  - Prints after Durand's paintings (Folder FF-14)
  - "Elias Boudinot L.L.D.", 1825 (Folder FF-15)
    Engraved by A.B. Durand. Painted by Waldo & Jewett. Published by E. Huntington, Hartford: 1825. Copyright secured April 30, 1822.
    Gift, Stephen Manheimer, July 2021.